Now that we've seen what a derivative
means and what it has to do with rates
of change, our next step is to learn how
to actually compute these guys. As in,
if I give you some kind of function with
an explicit formula, you'd want to be
able to find what the formula for its
derivative is.
Maybe it's obvious, but I think it's
worth stating explicitly why this is an
important thing to be able to do. Why
much of a calculus student's time ends
up going towards grappling with
derivatives of abstract functions rather
than thinking about concrete rate of
change problems.
It's because a lot of real-world
phenomena, the sort of things that we
want to use calculus to analyze, are
modeled using polynomials, trigonometric
functions, exponentials, and other pure
functions like that.
So, if you build up some fluency with
the ideas of rates of change for those
kinds of pure abstract functions, it
gives you a language to more readily
talk about the rates at which things
change in concrete situations that you
might be using calculus to model.
But, it is way too easy for this process
to feel like just memorizing a list of
rules. And if that happens, if you get
that feeling, it's also easy to lose
sight of the fact that derivatives are
fundamentally about just looking at tiny
changes to some quantity and how that
relates to a resulting tiny change in
another quantity.
So, in this video and in the next one,
my aim is to show you how you can think
about a few of these rules intuitively
and geometrically. And I really want to
encourage you to never forget that tiny
nudges are at the heart of derivatives.
Let's start with a simple function like
f of x equals x squared. What if I asked
you its derivative?
That is, if you were to look at some
value x, like x equals 2, and compare it
to a value slightly bigger, just dx
bigger, what's the corresponding change
in the value of the function, df?
And in particular, what's df divided by
dx? The rate at which this function is
changing per unit change in x.
As a first step for intuition, we know
that you can think of this ratio df dx
as the slope of a tangent line to the
graph of x squared.
And from that, you can see that the
slope generally increases as x
increases. At zero, the tangent line is
flat and the slope is zero.
At x equals one, it's something a bit
steeper.
At x equals two, it's steeper still.
But looking at graphs isn't generally
the best way to understand the precise
formula for a derivative.
For that, it's best to take a more
literal look at what x squared actually
means. And in this case, let's go ahead
and picture a square whose side length
is x.
If you increase x by some tiny nudge,
some little dx, what's the resulting
change in the area of that square?
That slight change in area is what df
means in this context. It's the tiny
increase to the value of f of x equals x
squared caused by increasing x by that
tiny nudge dx.
Now, you can see that there's three new
bits of area in this diagram. Two thin
rectangles and a minuscule square.
The two thin rectangles each have side
lengths of x and dx. So, they account
for two times x times dx units of new
area.
For example, let's say x was three and
dx was 0.01.
Then that new area from these two thin
rectangles would be two times three
times 0.01, which is 0.06. About six
times the size of dx.
That little square there has an area of
dx squared. But you should think of that
as being really tiny, negligibly tiny.
For example, if dx was 0.01, that would
be only 0.0001.
And keep in mind, I'm drawing dx with a
fair bit of width here just so we can
actually see it. But always remember, in
principle, dx should be thought of as a
truly tiny amount.
And for those truly tiny amounts, a good
rule of thumb is that you can ignore
anything that includes a DX raised to a
power greater than one.
That is a tiny change squared is a
negligible change.
What this leaves us with is that DF is
just some multiple of DX.
And that multiple, 2X, which you could
also write as DF divided by DX, is the
derivative of X squared.
For example, if you were starting at X
equals 3, then as you slightly increase
X, the rate of change in the area per
unit change in length added, DX squared
over DX, would be 2 * 3, or 6.
And if instead you were starting at X
equals 5, then the rate of change would
be 10 units of area per unit change in
X.
Let's go ahead and try a different
simple function, f of x equals x cubed.
This is going to be the geometric view
of the stuff that I went through
algebraically in the last video.
What's nice here is that we can think of
x cubed as the volume of an actual cube
whose side lengths are x.
And when you increase x by a tiny nudge,
a tiny DX, the resulting increase in
volume is what I have here in yellow.
That represents all the volume in a cube
with side lengths x plus DX that's not
already in the original cube, the one
with side length x.
It's nice to think of this new volume as
broken up into multiple components, but
almost all of it comes from these three
square faces.
Or said a little more precisely, as DX
approaches zero, those three squares
comprise a portion closer and closer to
100% of that new yellow volume.
Each of those thin squares has a volume
of x squared times DX, the area of the
face times that little thickness DX. So
in total, this gives us 3 x squared DX
of volume change.
And to be sure, there are other slivers
of volume here along the edges and that
tiny one in the corner, but all of that
volume is going to be proportional to dx
squared or dx cubed, so we can safely
ignore them.
Again, this is ultimately because
they're going to be divided by dx.
And if there's still any dx remaining,
then those terms aren't going to survive
the process of letting dx approach zero.
What this means is that the derivative
of x cubed, the rate at which x cubed
changes per unit change of x, is 3 * x
squared.
What that means in terms of graphical
intuition is that the slope of the graph
of x cubed at every single point x is
exactly 3x squared.
And reasoning about that slope, it
should make sense that this derivative
is high on the left and then zero at the
origin and then high again as you move
to the right, but just thinking in terms
of the graph would never have landed us
on the precise quantity 3x squared.
For that, we had to take a much more
direct look at what x cubed actually
means.
Now, in practice, you wouldn't
necessarily think of the square every
time you're taking the derivative of x
squared, nor would you necessarily think
of this cube whenever you're taking the
derivative of x cubed. Both of them fall
under a pretty recognizable pattern for
polynomial terms.
The derivative of x to the fourth turns
out to be 4x cubed, the derivative of x
to the fifth is 5x to the fourth and so
on.
Abstractly, you'd write this as the
derivative of x to the n for any power n
is n * x to the n - 1.
This right here is what's known in the
business as the power rule.
In practice, we all quickly just get
jaded and think about this symbolically
as the exponent hopping down in front,
leaving behind one less than itself,
rarely pausing to think about the
geometric delights that underlie these
derivatives.
That's the kind of thing that happens
when these tend to fall in the middle of
much longer computations.
But rather than chalking it all off to
symbolic patterns, let's just take a
moment and think about why this works
for powers beyond just two and three.
When you nudge that input X, increasing
it slightly to X + DX, working out the
exact value of that nudged output would
involve multiplying together these n
separate X + DX terms. The full
expansion would be really complicated,
but part of the point of derivatives is
that most of that complication can be
ignored.
The first term in your expansion is X to
the n. This is analogous to the area of
the original square
or the volume of the original cube from
our previous examples.
For the next terms in the expansion, you
can choose mostly X's with a single DX.
Since there are n different
parentheticals from which you could have
chosen that single DX, this gives us n
separate terms, all of which include n
minus one X's times a DX, giving a value
of X to the power n minus one times DX.
This is analogous to how the majority of
the new area in the square came from
those two bars, each with area X times
DX, or how the bulk of the new volume in
the cube came from those three thin
squares, each of which had a volume of X
squared times DX.
There will be many other terms in this
expansion, but all of them are just
going to be some multiple of DX squared,
so we can safely ignore them. And what
that means is that all but a negligible
portion of the increase in the output
comes from n copies of this X to the n
minus one times DX. That's what it means
for the derivative of X to the n to be n
times X to the n - 1.
And even though, like I said, in
practice, you'll find yourself
performing this derivative quickly and
symbolically, imagining the exponent
hopping down to the front,
every now and then, it's nice to just
step back and remember why these rules
work.
Not just because it's pretty, and not
just because it helps remind us that
math actually makes sense and isn't just
a pile of formulas to memorize,
but because it flexes that very
important muscle of thinking about
derivatives in terms of tiny nudges.
As another example, think of the
function f of x = 1 / x.
Now, on the one hand, you could just
blindly try applying the power rule,
since 1 / x is the same as writing x ^
-1.
That would involve letting the -1 hop
down in front, leaving behind one less
than itself, which is -2.
But let's have some fun and see if we
can reason about this geometrically,
rather than just plugging it through
some formula.
The value 1 / x is asking, "What number
multiplied by x = 1?"
So, here's how I'd like to visualize it.
Imagine a little rectangular puddle of
water sitting in two dimensions, whose
area is one.
And let's say that its width is x, which
means that the height has to be 1 / x,
since the total area of it is one.
So, if x was stretched out to two, then
that height is forced down to 1/2.
And if you increased x up to three, then
the other side has to be squished down
to 1/3.
This is a nice way to think about the
graph of 1 / x, by the way.
If you think of this width x of the
puddle as being in the xy-plane, then
that corresponding output 1 / x, the
height of the graph above that point, is
whatever the height of your puddle has
to be to maintain an area of one.
So, with this visual in mind, for the
derivative, imagine nudging up that
value of x by some tiny amount, some
tiny dx.
How must the height of this rectangle
change so that the area of the puddle
remains constant at one?
That is, increasing the width by dx adds
some new area to the right here. So, the
puddle has to decrease in height by some
d 1/x so that the area lost off of that
top cancels out the area gained.
You should think of that d 1/x as being
a negative amount, by the way, since
it's decreasing the height of the
rectangle.
And you know what? I'm going to leave
the last few steps here for you, for you
to pause and ponder and work out an
ultimate expression.
And once you reason out what d of 1/x
divided by dx should be, I want you to
compare it to what you would have gotten
if you had just blindly applied the
power rule purely symbolically to x to
the negative one.
And while I'm encouraging you to pause
and ponder, here's another fun challenge
if you're feeling up to it.
See if you can reason through what the
derivative of the square root of x
should be.
To finish things off, I want to tackle
one more type of function, trigonometric
functions. And in particular, let's
focus on the sine function.
So, for this section, I'm going to
assume that you're already familiar with
how to think about trig functions using
the unit circle, the circle with the
radius one centered at the origin.
For a given value of theta, like say
0.8, you imagine yourself walking around
the circle starting from the rightmost
point until you've traversed that
distance of 0.8 in arc length.
This is the same thing as saying that
the angle right here is exactly theta
radians since the circle has a radius of
one.
Then, what sine of theta means is the
height of that point above the x-axis.
And as your theta value increases and
you walk around the circle, your height
bobs up and down between -1 and 1.
So, when you graph sin of theta versus
theta, you get this wave pattern, the
quintessential wave pattern.
And just from looking at this graph, we
can start to get a feel for the shape of
the derivative of the sine.
The slope at zero is something positive,
since sin of theta is increasing there.
And as we move to the right and sin of
theta approaches its peak, that slope
goes down to zero.
Then the slope is negative for a little
while, while the sine is decreasing,
before coming back up to zero as the
sine graph levels out.
And as you continue thinking this
through and drawing it out, if you're
familiar with the graph of trig
functions, you might guess that this
derivative graph should be exactly
cosine of theta, since all the peaks and
valleys line up perfectly with where the
peaks and valleys for the cosine
function should be.
And spoiler alert, the derivative is in
fact the cosine of theta.
But aren't you a little curious about
why it's precisely cosine of theta? I
mean, you could have all sorts of
functions with peaks and valleys at the
same points that have roughly the same
shape, but who knows? Maybe the
derivative of sine could have turned out
to be some entirely new type of function
that just happens to have a similar
shape.
Well, just like the previous examples, a
more exact understanding of the
derivative requires looking at what the
function actually represents, rather
than looking at the graph of the
function.
So, think back to that walk around the
unit circle.
Having traversed an arc with length
theta, and thinking about sin of theta
as the height of that point.
Now, zoom in to that point on the
circle, and consider a slight nudge of d
theta along their circumference, a tiny
step in your walk around the unit
circle.
How much does that tiny step change the
sin of theta?
How much does this increase d theta of
arc length increase the height above the
x-axis?
Well, zoomed in close enough, the circle
basically looks like a straight line in
this neighborhood. So, let's go ahead
and think of this right triangle, where
the hypotenuse of that right triangle
represents the nudge d theta along the
circumference. And that left side here
represents the change in height, the
resulting d sine of theta.
Now, this tiny triangle is actually
similar to this larger triangle here
with the defining angle theta and whose
hypotenuse is the radius of the circle
with length one.
Specifically, this little angle right
here is precisely equal to theta
radians.
Now, think about what the derivative of
sine is supposed to mean.
It's the ratio between that d sine of
theta, the tiny change to the height,
divided by d theta, the tiny change to
the input of the function.
And from the picture, we can see that
that's the ratio between the length of
the side adjacent to the angle theta
divided by the hypotenuse.
Well, let's see. Adjacent divided by
hypotenuse? That's exactly what the
cosine of theta means. That's the
definition of the cosine.
So, this gives us two different really
nice ways of thinking about how the
derivative of sine is cosine.
One of them is looking at the graph and
getting a loose feel for the shape of
things based on thinking about the slope
of the sine graph at every single point.
And the other is a more precise line of
reasoning, looking at the unit circle
itself.
For those of you that like to pause and
ponder, see if you can try a similar
line of reasoning to find what the
derivative of the cosine of theta should
be.
In the next video, I'll talk about how
you can take derivatives of functions
who combine simple functions like these
ones, either as sums or products or
function compositions, things like that.
And similar to this video, the goal is
going to be to understand each one
geometrically in a way that makes it
intuitively reasonable and somewhat more
memorable.
Mhm.